<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE recipeml PUBLIC "-//FormatData//DTD RecipeML 0.5//EN" "http://www.formatdata.com/recipeml/recipeml.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="nsRecipe.xml" type="text/xsl"?>
<recipeml version="0.5"
          xmlns="http://www.formatdata.com/recipeml/recipeml.dtd"
          xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
		  >
  <meta content="Wednesday December 28, 2005" name="DC.Date"/>
  <meta content="Maria Mannherz" name="DC.Creator"/>
  <recipe id="Haselnussbr&#246;tchen">
    <head>
      <title>Haselnussbr&#246;tchen</title>
      <subtitle>Hazelnut Meringues</subtitle>
      <categories>
        <cat class="main">Cookies</cat>
        <cat class="sub">Meringue</cat>
        <cat class="region">Germany</cat>
        <cat class="diet">dairy-free</cat>
        <cat class="diet">gluten-free</cat>
      </categories>
    </head>
    <description><xhtml:p>In German, a Broetchen is a little bread; therefore,
    these are little hazelnut breads. Gran'ma rarely made these because she
    could never chop the nuts finely enough, she said. However, with a food
    processor, this is a very easy recipe. The only problem I had was not
    knowing the shape of the cookies to make. The first time, I, for an
    unknown reason, decided they should be bar cookies. It became a delicious
    failure.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>Save seven of the yolks for Ausstecherle, and the remaining yolk
    for glazing the Ausstecherle.</xhtml:p>
	</description>
    <ingredients system="US">
      <ing-div>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>1 1/2</qty>
            <unit>lb</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>hazelnuts</item>
<!--1 1/2 lb chopped hazelnuts-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>8</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>egg whites</item>
<!--8 egg whites-->
        </ing>
        <ing optional="yes">
          <amt>
            <qty>1/2</qty>
            <unit>tsp</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>cream of tartar</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>2 1/2</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>sugar</item>
<!--2 1/2 c. sugar-->
        </ing>
      </ing-div>
    </ingredients>
    <directions>
      <step>Preheat oven to <temp><qty>325</qty><tempunit unit="F"
      system="US">degrees</tempunit><!--350  degrees--></temp>.</step>

      <step optional="yes">While the oven is preheating, spread the nuts on a
      baking sheet and toast for five or six minutes, shaking once midway
      through.</step>

      <step>Grind the hazelnuts in a food processor until very finely chopped.
      This will take a minute or minute and a half for each bowlful. If you
      wish, reserve and chop about 1/4 cup of nuts to use as
      decorations.</step>

      <step>In a large (4 1/2 qt) bowl, beat the egg whites until stiff.
      Slowly add the sugar while continuing to beat. Once the sugar is added,
      beat until stiff peaks form and the mixture is glossy. Fold in the
      ground nuts.</step>

      <step>Drop small spoonfuls onto a parchment-paper-covered cookie sheet,
      <xhtml:i>or</xhtml:i> fill a large pastry bag fitted with a very large,
      plain tip (I use a #809), and pipe circles of meringue. This may seem
      like overkill, but I found it was easier and faster to pipe the
      cookies.</step>

      <step optional="yes">Smooth the tops of the cookies with a finger or the
      back of a spoon dipped in water. Place a reserved nut piece on the
      center of each cookie. </step>

      <step>Bake 25 to 30 minutes or until light brown. Essentially, the
      cookies will dry out.</step>
    </directions>
  </recipe>
</recipeml>
