<recpiml version="0.5">
  <meta name="DC.Date">1 December, 2003</meta>
  <recipe>
    <description><xhtml:p>Pfeffernuesse are as German as cookies get. Spicy
	like Lebkuchen, firm like Springerle, these cookies come from what
	the German's call the &quot;Oma Zeit,&quot; the grandmother's time.
	Traditionally, hard cookies like Pfeffernuesse were meant to be
	dunked into wine during a long session of visiting and cookie
	eating, according to Chef Fritz Blank of Duex Cheminees.

	To be honest, I never liked Pfeffernuesse; one of the main
	ingredients is citron or orangeat, also known as fruit cake mix.
	This version is a little new wave, substituting crystalized ginger
	for the citron, and a little neo-traditional, keeping the ground
	pepper that gives these &quot;pepper nuts&quot; their name.</xhtml:p></description>
    <head>
      <categories>
        <cat>German</cat>
        <cat>cookie</cat>
      </categories>
      <title>Pfeffernuesse</title>
      <subtitle>Peppernut</subtitle>
    </head>
    <directions>
      <dir-div>
        <title>The first day</title>
        <step>Whip together eggs and sugar on high speed until
			tripled in volume and almost white, about three to five
			minutes. Finely chop crystalized ginger or citron; grind
			nuts. Add crystalized ginger (or citron), nuts and lemon
			zest or extract to egg mixture and mix until combined.
			Change to the paddle blade. Sift together spices, flour and
			baking powder, and slowly add to eggs mixture. If the dough
			is dry and  crumbly, add milk one tablespoon at a time until
			dough holds together. Knead gently for a minute or two until
			the dough is smooth. Cover and let sit for one day; this
			step is important to allow the flavors to meld.</step>
      </dir-div>
      <dir-div>
        <title>The second day</title>
        <step>Preheat oven to 325 degrees. Form dough
			into balls about 1 to 1 1/2 inches in diameter; place on a
			parchment covered baking sheet. Bake 20 to 25 minutes until
			browned. Allow to cool 20 minutes.</step>
        <step>In a small bowl, whisk together powdered sugar and
			lemon juice; add a bit of hot water for a thinner glaze if
			you like. Dip the tops of the cookies into the glaze and
			allow excess to drip off. (A cooling rack placed over the
			parchement-lined baking sheets works well.) Store in an
			airtight container. These keep for a long time, and the
			flavor improves with age.</step>
      </dir-div>
    </directions>
    <ingredients>
      <ing-div>
        <title>For the cookie</title>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit></unit>
            <qty>2</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>eggs</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>g</unit>
            <qty>300</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>sugar</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>59.14705925</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>candied ginger</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>g</unit>
            <qty>40</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>almonds</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <alt-ing>
            <amt>
              <unit></unit>
              <qty></qty>
            </amt>
            <item>zest of 1/2 lemon</item>
          </alt-ing>
          <alt-ing>
            <amt>
              <unit>mL</unit>
              <qty>2.46446080208333</qty>
            </amt>
            <item>lemon extract</item>
          </alt-ing>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>g</unit>
            <qty>326.25</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>flour</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>4.92892160416667</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>baking powder</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>4.92892160416667</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>cinnamon</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>2.46446080208333</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>ground cloves</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>2.46446080208333</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>ground cardamom</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>2.46446080208333</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>ground ginger</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>1.23223040104167</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>ground pepper</item>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>mL</unit>
            <qty>59.14705925</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>milk</item>
        </ing>
      </ing-div>
      <ing-div>
        <title>For the glaze</title>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit>g</unit>
            <qty>172.5</qty>
          </amt>
          <item>powdered sugar</item>
          <prep>sifted</prep>
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <unit></unit>
            <qty></qty>
          </amt>
          <item>juice of 1/2 lemon</item>
        </ing>
      </ing-div>
    </ingredients>
  </recipe>
</recpiml>
