<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE recipeml PUBLIC "-//FormatData//DTD RecipeML 0.5//EN" "http://www.formatdata.com/recipeml/recipeml.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="nsRecipe.xml" type="text/xsl"?>
<recipeml version="0.5"
          xmlns="http://www.formatdata.com/recipeml/recipeml.dtd"
          xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
		  >
  <recipe id="rum_balls">
  <meta content="Sunday January  8, 2006" name="DC.Date"/>
  <meta content="Mom" name="DC.Creator"/>
    <head>
      <title>Rum Balls</title>
      <categories>
        <cat class="main">Cookies</cat>
        <cat class="region">America</cat>
        <cat class="diet">Egg-free</cat>
      </categories>
    </head>
    <description><xhtml:p>Baking teaches many things. These cookies, for example, taught me to ask every person about food allergies, after poisoning a friend who is allergic to nuts. He's fine, but had an unpleasant after-Christmas party.</xhtml:p>

<xhtml:p>These are the most popular cookie every year, and are extremely simple, requiring no baking at all.</xhtml:p>

<xhtml:p>Once you've mastered these, try the more sophisticated B-52 Balls.</xhtml:p></description>
    <ingredients system="US">
      <ing-div>
	  	<title>Dough</title>
        <ing>
<!--1 c. ground pecans-->
          <amt>
            <qty>1</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>walnuts</item>
<!--1 c. ground walnuts-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>1</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>vanilla wafers</item>
<!--1 c. crushed vanilla wafers-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>1</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>confectioners sugar</item>
<!--1 c. confectioners sugar-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>2</qty>
            <unit>Tb</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>cocoa</item>
<!--2 Tb. cocoa-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <range>
              <q1>1 1/2</q1>
              <q2>2 1/2</q2>
            </range>
            <unit>Tb</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>corn syrup</item>
<!--1 1/2 to 2 1/2 Tb corn syrup-->
        </ing>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>1/4</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>rum</item>
<!--1/4 c. rum-->
<!--1/4 c. bourbon-->
        </ing>
      </ing-div>
      <ing-div>
	  	<title>Sugar for dusting</title>
        <ing>
          <amt>
            <qty>1</qty>
            <unit>c</unit>
          </amt>
          <item>confectioners sugar</item>
<!--extra confectioners sugar -->
        </ing>
      </ing-div>
    </ingredients>
    <directions>
      <step>Grind the nuts in a food processor until very finely chopped. This will take a minute or minute and a half. Mix crushed (fine, but not to a powder!) cookies, nuts, <ing><amt><qty>1</qty> <unit>c</unit></amt> <item>confectioners sugar</item></ing> and cocoa. Add combined syrup and rum. Mix together with your hands until it can be compressed into a ball. If the dough is too crumbly, add more corn syrup a teaspoon at a time.</step>
      <step>The dough can be made completely in the food processor. Start by grinding the nuts, then add the wafers and pulse to break them up. Add the cocoa and <ing><amt><qty>1</qty> <unit>c</unit></amt> <item>confectioners sugar</item></ing>, sifted if desired, and pulse until the cocoa is evenly distributed. Add the rum and corn syrup, and process on low speed until the mixture comes together. If the misture doesn't come together, add more corn syrup one teaspoon at a time.</step>
      <step>Smush the mixture together tightly into a ball or disk, and wrap in plastic wrap or store in an airtight container. Let sit for a few days in the refrigerator; the dough improves with age.</step>
      <step>Pinch off a piece of dough, and compact it into a rough ball shape, about <size><qty>3/4</qty> <unit>inch</unit></size> in diameter. The dough will want to stick to your hands more than itself. Roll between your palms to smooth out. Roll in confectioners sugar. Store in an airtight container.</step>

      <note type="variation" title="Bourbon balls">Substitute pecans for the walnuts, and bourbon for the rum..</note>
    </directions>
  </recipe>
</recipeml>
